Let's pray.
Well, good morning, church. Thank you all for being with us this morning as we round out our series on Christian witness, the practice of Christian witness, and just the
reality that in this practicing the way series that we're not called to just fill our head with more information, but to actively do the thing God is calling us to do. So far, we've said that this is not just a unique gift for a select few, but it is a calling for on the life of every individual believer. Jesus, one of the last thing that he says to his followers before he ascended into his rightful place at the throne of God, he said, "You will receive power from the
Holy Spirit, and you will be my witnesses in Jerusalem, Judea, and to the ends of the earth." This is a calling on every follower of Jesus, and we are here because they did the thing that God invited them to do. They went from Jerusalem to Judea, to the ends of the earth, sharing the gospel. And it was not often a many people come to hear one person listen. It was relationally spread throughout the whole empire and beyond. But sharing the gospel is
often slow and loving in a relational process. This series has not just been about throwing gospel tracks on the table and walking away. It's not primarily about knocking on strangers' doors, although I will not limit the fact that the Holy Spirit might invite you to do that. It's not just about memorizing the Roman's road. It's about demonstrating and declaring the reign and rule of Jesus where we live, work, and play. It has to be motivated by genuine love for people who don't know Jesus, not viewing them as
spiritual projects, but genuinely caring about them as image bearers of their Creator. It's rooted in hospitality, which is the process of us opening up our homes and our lives for others to see the glory of Jesus in the broken mess that we bring to them. And it requires an active participation with the Holy Spirit. Remember the verse I just quoted, "You will receive power when the Holy Spirit comes upon you."
We aren't just bringing God to a place that he already isn't. We're actively revealing where he's been at work this whole time. And today I want to wrap up the series talking about how we can creatively share the gospel in clear and compelling ways, because it's great to demonstrate the gospel of Jesus, and we should do it. And our declaration should be rooted in demonstration, but demonstration is not enough to get people to the place where they repent of their rebellion towards God and pursue a relationship with him through Jesus.
We have to proclaim the gospel of Jesus in order for people to understand the invitation that they are receiving. We have to share the good news of Jesus. So, we're going to hopefully talk about how we can do that in a creative, clear, and compelling way. Sound good? Cool. Let's pray.
Father, we again are grateful for another opportunity to gather together with our spiritual family in this local body.
And we acknowledge that we are one of millions of local expressions of your kingdom all across this world.
And we are just excited to participate with you in the invitation that you've given us to spread that good news, to announce that story everywhere we go.
And so God, calm our fears, give us boldness, excitement, and creativity as we think about the people that you've placed in our life that have yet to surrender their selves to you.
God, give us just excitement and creativity to find ways to share that story and release the outcome to you. God, we do not save anyone. You save them, but there is power in the proclamation of the good news of Jesus.
The gospel is the power of God for salvation to all who believe. So God, just help us in this endeavor as we stumble in participation with you. It's in Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
So I talked to the individual that's leading the elementary school class this morning, and I told them that teaching children is really not that much different than teaching adults.
This morning, our primary illustration for the day is going to be a Buzz Lightyear toy that I had to beg my child to let me borrow, and he said no a few times, but finally he allowed it.
I recently re-watched the great Pixar classic Toy Story with Rory in preparation to take him to the movie theaters for the first time. I think we have a picture so that we can all say, "Aww."
He quickly latched onto the character of Buzz Lightyear, and I've been thinking a lot about this character this week as I've studied 1 Peter 2, which is where we're going to eventually be in your Bibles if you want to turn there, 1 Peter 2.
See, Buzz is a confident individual when he arrives on the scene in Andy's bedroom. Some might even say overconfident in the story that he believes he's living in.
Space Ranger, Star Command. Defeat Zerg and go home, right? He's confident. He knows who he is. Everything around him reinforces the identity that he believes about himself,
from his uniform to the packaging on the box to the laser on his arm, which apparently this toy does not have because I got the cheap version at TJ Maxx.
Actually, it wasn't that cheap either, which is kind of disappointing now that I think about it. Everything about his life reinforces the story.
The problem is that the story that Buzz knows about himself is only a small portion of the actual story that he's living into.
The things that we just said are false information. It is true. Part of his identity is that he is Buzz Lightyear from Star Command to defeat Zerg, right?
This is a part of who he is, but it's only a small part of who he is. More importantly, he's a toy.
He belongs to Andy, and he was made for the purpose of bringing Andy joy. His true identity only makes sense in the fuller version of his story.
As long as he's focused on just the small bits and pieces of his identity that are reinforced by his uniform and his packaging, he's going to miss the point that he was made for.
And this really is how the gospel of the New Testament works in the lives of believers.
And what we have to understand if we're going to learn to effectively witness in a clear and compelling way to the world around us.
The gospel is not a few spiritual facts we add to the story of our lives that we're already living in.
It's not a religious formula we work through to get our sins forgiven so we can go to heaven when we die.
It is so much more than that.
It is an announcement. The gospel is a proclamation of a story that we are actually living in.
It is a proclamation that the story that we are living in is bigger than we've realized.
It's better than we've realized. It has more to it than we've realized or previously understood.
It's really the only story that can truly make sense of who we are and why we're here and what's gone wrong and how it can all be restored through Jesus.
The gospel is the announcement of the story we were created to live in.
I love how Pastor John Tyson says it. He says this, "We have to be re-narrated out of our story."
The story of self, the story of other gods, the story of our culture, and into the story of Jesus.
It's a re-narration of the identity that we live in, that all of us were made for, and yet we often understand a small sliver of the pie.
But the gospel re-narrates us. Jesus reveals the true story that we're living in and teaches us to understand ourselves and our world around us from his story's perspective.
And this is exactly what Peter is going to do to his original audience in 1 Peter 2. And if I'm honest, it's honestly what most of the New Testament letters are doing.
Most of the New Testament letters are helping believers who might be struggled to believe something false about their story, to point them to the truest story that they're living in because of the gospel of Jesus,
and help them to understand how living in that story will change the way they think and behave moving forward.
So my hope is that we see in 1 Peter 2 how this re-narration helps us, first and foremost, understand who we are and what we're called to.
And then secondly, will give us real clear ideas of how we can announce that story to those who have yet to receive it.
So if you want to read with me 1 Peter 2, we will start for now in verse...let's go 9.
Peter says, "But you are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for God's own possession, so that you may proclaim the excellencies of him who called you out of darkness and into marvelous light.
Once you were not a people, but now you are God's people. Once you had not received mercy, but now you have received mercy."
The original audience that Peter was writing to was predominantly Gentile converts to Christianity who had been persecuted for their faith by their unconverted neighbors, family, and friends.
And what Peter here is doing in this short section is he's helping them understand the story that they're actually living in, because they might feel discouraged being persecuted for believing in Jesus resurrected from the dead.
When everything around them is going in the opposite direction, and they could easily just give up on this and go back to the way things were, where they weren't being persecuted, where life wasn't as difficult.
And yet Peter wants them to understand that the reason that they are suffering is because they have embraced a story that is truer than the story everyone else around them is living in.
And therefore it's going to be hard for now, but if they remember who they are, they can persevere and be faithful.
They might be tempted to think they're forgotten by God. They might have maybe even feel, maybe I've clung to a false religion or an ideology.
Maybe I was persuaded to believe something that isn't true, which could lead to anger or walking away from the faith.
But Peter says the reason they are suffering is because of their new identity in Christ. Royal priesthood, holy nation, set apart people.
And he anchors this claim in the Old Testament story.
He's quoting here from Exodus 19 verses five and six, which is God's covenant with Israel at Mount Sinai.
Which as I was studying, I had to like double check my notes because most of the commentators were saying that Peter's original audience was Gentile converts.
I don't know about you, but I was thinking, why quote the Mosaic covenant to a bunch of Gentile converts from the first century, right?
Like, what is this going to do from them? This is not their story. This is the Israelite story.
And so what is Peter doing in quoting the Exodus story, God's covenant with the nation of Israel?
It might seem strange at first, but we have to remember that the Bible is actually one unified story about God partnering with people to demonstrate his goodness.
To all creation. And so what I have to, what I think I have to do right now is do a quick theological detour from first Peter to we'll come back and land the plane.
I think it will pay off. I've ran this through my head, hypothetically, a couple of times. It's very possible it doesn't work.
So that's what we're going to do. Okay. It's going to work. Thank you, Dave. I appreciate it.
The Bible is one unified story. The Mosaic covenant is God inviting the people of Israel back into humanity's original story before sin entered the world.
So when we pull the thread back to Exodus, we need to not stop there. We need to keep pulling the thread back to Genesis.
Just like Adam and Eve, God wants to partner with Israel to bless the entire world through them. This is his pursuing God, pursuing people to do the thing they were originally created to do.
It's him showing them that you were made for a bigger story than the story that you are living in. You were made to be in relationship with me and to demonstrate my goodness to the world around you.
At the center of this partnership in Israel was the tabernacle and the priests. The tabernacle was where God's presence would dwell, and the priests who dwelt in God's presence would represent him to the world around them.
And I would argue that when Peter quotes Exodus 19, he's not only thinking about the tabernacle and the priests in the Mosaic covenant, but he's also thinking about this entire biblical theme of God partnering with people
to dwell in his presence and to bless the world around him, to be in his presence and to be a representation of him to the world around him. This is at the heart of the Eden story.
Tim Mackey and other scholars have pointed out that both the tabernacle and the priestly responsibilities are symbols and models of what is described in the Garden of Eden before the fall.
That this is all one unified story, that what God invites Israel into, what God invites Abraham into, is the same thing that he was inviting Adam and Eve into when they failed.
Israel's tabernacle is constructed as an echo of the Garden of Eden, with the spaces getting holier and holier until you get to the center of the tabernacle where God's presence would dwell.
The command to work and keep given to Adam and Eve in the garden is the same words that are described to use the priestly duties in the tabernacle.
This is all one story. God wants to partner with people to demonstrate and declare his rule and reign to all of creation.
The thing we've been inviting you to from the beginning of this series is just the same thing that God was inviting Adam and Eve to at the very beginning of the story.
This is the story of God. God wants to partner with people in relationships so that his presence can fill them and they can take his goodness to all creation.
Humanity's original vocation was to be priests, and their tabernacle was all of creation. This is the beginning of the story.
But the story shrinks because sin enters the world. Now no longer are all of humanity God's priests and all of creation his tabernacle, but now it gets shrunken down to where select people are invited to partner with God to be priests, and the tabernacle is centered in one geographic location.
And all of this happens as a result of sin. Sin is what takes God's original plan south, and that is why sin is such a big deal.
I think, I don't know, for those of you that grew up in the church, sometimes we disconnect sin from what it's actually doing, the damage that it's actually causing, and we so fixate it on a few lists of behaviors that people don't want us to do.
And sometimes that can feel weird and legalistic and checkboxy, but the reason sin is such a big deal, because at the end of the day, it's usurping God's story for our own story.
It's usurping His authority, His rule, His reign, His presence for our own. It's shrinking the story we were made for, and ultimately, because of that, it impacts the ability for God's goodness to spread to the whole world.
The reason the world is broken is because humans stopped partnering with God to bring about His goodness to all creation. We usurped His authority. We exchanged His story for our own, and when we usurp God's authority for our own, we end up looking like Buzz.
We build our identity and our existence on part of the story. It's not that the things that Buzz knows about himself are wrong. It's just that they're half of the truth. They're part of the truth.
They're a shrunken version of the truth, and this is often what image bearers do when we rebel against God because of our sin. It's not that everything we believe is false.
It's that it's a shrunken version of the true story we're invited into, and we try and find fulfillment and satisfaction and identity in less than we were made for.
And this is the gospel. The good news is that God doesn't give up on people when we rebel against His plan.
Not only is He good, but He's merciful. He keeps pursuing us. He keeps pursuing humans.
It starts with Abraham and moves on to the nation of Israel through Moses and David, and on and on we could go.
The whole story is one unified story about God drawing people back from their rebellion, back from their partial story,
and inviting them to participate in His story again, to be priests and tabernacles of God's presence to the world around them,
so that they might be blessed, so that they might understand who God is and what they were made for.
And Israel has seasons of partial faithfulness, but on the whole they fail miserably.
And if you're ever frustrated reading the Old Testament, or you ever think, "How in the world could God call these people His people?"
That's the point. And too often when we study the Old Testament, and I've been in Bible studies,
where we try and like take horrific characters and moralize them and make it seem like they're good people, they're not.
And that's kind of the point. The point is that God continues to partner with broken people to restore and redeem the world by the power of His Holy Spirit.
And so Israel has partial seasons of success, but mostly they fail. They continue to usurp God's authority and shrink the story
until the best news of the good news, the second Adam, the faithful Israel, the promised seed of Mary, who would crush the head of the deceitful servant, steps onto the scene.
Jesus is the culmination of God's story. The gospel is Jesus making a way for humanity to be re-narrated into the story we were made for.
He succeeds in the wilderness where Israel failed. He succeeds in the garden where Adam failed. He is our great high priest,
perfectly demonstrating who God is to the world and bringing people back to God through his sacrifice. This is what priests did.
They brought people back to God through his sacrifice, except they had to do it over and over and over again.
And Hebrews says, "Jesus, our great high priest, stepped down from heaven and made one sacrifice once and for all
so that he could bring humanity back to himself and he could extend his presence to them through the power of the Holy Spirit, his tabernacle and temple no longer
needing to be centralized in one geographic location, but now it goes with us everywhere we go because the Holy Spirit is in us and working through us.
The garden vocation has been restored. God is no longer settling for a few priests representing him in one geographic location.
Now, all of us who receive the gospel, the new story, the full version of the story, we become priests in temples and we take his presence with us everywhere we go.
Heaven coming to earth through humans who have been re-narrated to God through Jesus.
I think this is Peter's point when he says, "You are a chosen race, a royal priest, a holy nation of people for my own possession."
His application is that once we realize the bigger story we're a part of, it will change everything about us.
And he moves on and he says, "Because of that identity, because of who you are, because of how you understand the whole story of God and why you're here and what that means, it will change the way you behave."
Verse 11, he says, "Beloved, I urge you as sojourners, you're exiles now because you've embraced the story that your culture does not embrace, and that makes you foreign, alien.
You are now a part of a kingdom that is not of this world, which makes you an exile. And because of that, I need you to abstain from passions of the flesh, which wage war against your soul, and keep your behavior among the Gentiles honorable, so that when they speak against you as evil doers, they may see your good deeds and glorify God on the day of visitation."
Peter's point here is, as priests, as holy nation, your job is now to demonstrate and declare the reign of King Jesus everywhere you go.
Now, we've spent a lot of time in this series talking about the demonstrating part, the hospitality, the motivation of love, the looking for opportunities to be the hands and feet of Jesus.
And what I want to do now with the rest of our time, because of that theological timeout that hopefully helped, I want to talk about what, because that's the story, because that's the gospel.
How then do we think about creatively sharing that gospel? We're going to read later in chapter three with gentleness and respect.
Let's just go ahead and read it. So it's on the table. First Peter chapter three, verse 14, he says, "But even if you should suffer for righteousness sake, if you get mistreated,
if bad things happen to you for doing the thing God invited you to do," he says, "You will be blessed.
Have no fear of them, nor be troubled, but in your hearts honor Christ the Lord as holy,
always being prepared to make a defense to anyone who asks you for a reason for the hope that is in you.
Yet do it with gentleness and respect." This is what priests do. They sacrificially lay down their life, and they honor,
and they bless those who are persecuting them, and they look for opportunities to tell these people
of why we live differently. So to do so, I want to revisit our friend Buzz. Spoiler alert if you haven't seen
Toy Story 5, okay? Sorry, it's been out long enough. I'm sorry. You guys waited. 31 years after the original
Toy Story, Pixar brings this story full circle. In Toy Story 5, there are now 50 brand new high-tech Buzz Lightyear's living inside the same incomplete story.
They wash up on shore, and they're doing the Buzz Lightyear thing, right? Space Ranger, Star Command, defeat Zerg, go home.
But this time, there's a Buzz who knows who he really is. The truest story that all these Buzz's were created to live for.
And Buzz comes alongside them, and knowing their false story, their short-sighted nature of their story, he comes alongside them and helps them to see that their fullest and most complete identity is found in being a toy and finding an owner and bringing joy in that relationship.
He is declaring the good news of who Buzz Lightyear is. And this is how I want us to think about how we declare the gospel.
We declare the gospel to our friends and neighbors and coworkers. That's not just about memorizing the Roman's road and finding an awkward time to tell them that they're a sinner in need of a savior.
It's about helping them. It's about listening to them, hearing the story that they're living in, affirming the realities of that story that are true.
This is again where I get frustrated with some of the ways we share the gospel. It's like everything about you is wrong. It's like, no, you're an image bearer of the Most High God.
Some of the things inside of you that you're pursuing are good and God given and made for him to be used. And yet we're telling them, stop it.
It's like, no, like let's affirm the realities of their story that are true and then help them to see where they're putting too much emphasis on a smaller version of the story and how they're missing the point and invite them into a deeper and more beautiful understanding of who God made them to be.
This is what gospeling looks like. This is what sharing the gospel looks like. It's a re-narration of the story we were made for.
And it has to start with us, yes, living consistently like we actually believe what we say we believe, but then it goes to extending that invitation to others.
This is how I want us to think about kingdom witnesses. I was going to, at first I was thinking about using Woody, but then you read the part about Jesus.
Didn't you read the part about gentleness and respect? You're a toy! And I think that's often how we think about sharing the gospel.
It's like, hey, idiot, you're missing the point. It's like, no, that's not. What happens is in Toy Story 5 is Buzz is not like you're an idiot.
He's like, I know who you are. I know where you are because I was there. Let me listen and affirm and understand and with gentleness and compassion invite you into a bigger story that you were made for.
We're made for this is how we should think about the gospel. It's an announcement about the story we were created to be a part of.
And this is why it's, and somebody coming in just asked me what our next series is. Our next series is Scripture.
This is why it's so important we read and study our Bibles in community, because if we're going to effectively announce the story of God, we have to know it.
We have to know God's story inside and out. We have to believe it. We have to understand that the Old Testament,
that we don't have to moralize bad people in the Old Testament, because that's not the point.
I think sometimes we're so worried that people are going to see these warts in the Old Testament and think,
"Well, if that's the God of the Old Testament, I don't want to be a part of it."
It's like, "Well, if that's not the God of the Old Testament, then you're not invited, because He only works with broken people.
And if you're great, then you don't need Him. You're right. But we're all broken."
This is why it's so important we understand the story. Evangelism isn't memorizing a few Bible verses to quote back at people.
It's declaring the story of God. It's helping people to see how their stories are shrunken down.
And yes, some parts of their story are true, and we can affirm that, but it's missing the broader version.
So, as we begin to land the plane, I want to give you a helpful framework for how I think we can begin to creatively do this in relationship with people who don't yet know Jesus.
And I'm going to give a few examples of what this might look like. The goal here is not to memorize some arguments for some people.
It's just to show you how this could function in your life relationally and organically. I hope it works. If it doesn't, I'm sorry.
All right. Framework. So, the way I want us to think about this is first to listen for the story that the individuals in our lives are living in.
Listen to where their hopes and their dreams are. Listen to what they're looking for to find fulfillment and satisfaction.
Ask yourself these questions. What good things are they looking for? Where does that thing ask them to usurp God's glory?
And how does Jesus invite them into a fuller version of that story? So, we start by listening and affirming what is true.
And this process is slow. You don't get to have one 30-minute conversation with somebody and diagnose their worldview, okay?
I mean, maybe, but like temper yourself a little bit and maybe have a second conversation and don't go in thinking you already know everything about them.
Ask questions. Listen to understand. Affirm parts of the story that are true.
And when given the opportunity with gentleness and respect, ask questions that might expose how that story falls short of what they were actually created for.
And when given the opportunity, announce the gospel of Jesus to them.
So that's the framework.
Now let's do a couple of examples of how this might work in different worldviews, in different ideologies, in different shrunken parts of the story, because all of us, like Buzz, we have parts of the story, right?
And we can listen and affirm those things, and then look for opportunities to come alongside and announce the truest story that we were all made for.
This is going to fall. Okay, good.
We ready?
All right. First, and we could do a million of these, but most of them kind of I've seen fall into big categories.
And I just picked, I used words from, there's a book by Scott McKnight called "The King Jesus Gospel."
I'm now realizing I didn't put the source in my notes. So I stole it from him, and he, in his book, stole it from somebody else.
So we're like three things removed from the actual source, but if you go to the last chapter of "The King Jesus Gospel" by Scott McKnight, you can find it.
And he's just going through big picture worldviews. First, individualism.
The story of individualism is I am at the center of my universe. And again, that's why we listen carefully.
No one is going to look you in the eye and say, "You know, I really just think I am the center of my own universe."
It's not how these worldviews work, right? It's not how these ideologies work, but if you listen, you'll find this underlying current.
I'm the center of my universe. I can't be truly happy apart from living authentically to who I am.
We can affirm some things about that, right? We can affirm that you are uniquely valuable.
You are an image bearer. You are not an accident or some interchangeable part in a machine.
Your life, your gifts, your personality, your story, they are all important and they matter to God.
Yes and amen. We can expose that this story actually moves you from my life matters to I get to define what good means.
I become the ultimate authority of my life. I get to define good and evil for myself.
And right in there, we can hear the original lie.
You, and then we ask questions like, do you understand the weight of the authority that you are putting on your own shoulders?
You who cannot make your own bed. When you get up, like, okay, me. Me who cannot make my own bed.
Now I want to be the ultimate authority for what is good and all of life.
And we announce that the gospel says your identity isn't something that you have to invent or discover.
It can be received from the one who made you. God didn't just make you on purpose,
but for a purpose and true fulfillment, true life and meaning and purpose comes from submitting your personal identity,
not leaving that at the door. He made you the way he made you on purpose for a purpose.
You bring that to him, surrendering it to him for his cosmic purposes.
That's individualism, consumerism. My purpose is to have and experience as many good things as I can.
Again, probably not going to say, "You know what? I really think the meaning of life is things."
They're not going to tell you that. But like, you know, we've seen it. We've done it.
That's the beautiful thing about Buzz, right?
The reason he's such an empathetic witness to the identity of who he actually is is because he's been there.
We've been there. We've done that. We still do this. So we listen.
And we affirm that creation is a good gift to be enjoyed. The things that you want, the experiences, the nice things, that's made by God.
These are good things. Creation is good. But consumerism, this is where we expose, that consumerism takes a gift to be enjoyed and shared with others, and it turns it into a God, and it will never be enough.
And you will always find yourself gazing over your neighbor's fence, looking for the next thing that might satisfy you.
And it's not going to be enough. It's never enough. But Jesus frees you to enjoy creation without expecting it to fulfill you.
You were made for the enjoyment of creation, not the consumption of it, frees you up to not just enjoy good things, but share good things with others.
Thirdly, nationalism or tribalism says, "My nation or my tribe is where I find my identity. The success of my group
and the failure of my enemies is my highest aim." And pastorally, I'm going to say, I think this has creeped into the church
just as much as consumerism is, if consumerism has, if not more. My nation or my tribe, we're so disunified as a nation
that we've shrunken it to not my nation, but my political party within my nation. This is where I find my ultimate hope,
and my identity. And the success of my group is how I will succeed and find flourishing in life. And the gnarly side of that
is that in order for that to happen, the people who are outside of your tribe become your enemies, and you get to justify
doing a lot of horrible things to them so that your group gets to win. Now, we affirm some of the beautiful realities
in this nation's languages and people groups matter to God. The book of Revelation actually indicates
that every culture has a unique glory it brings before God. There are unique things about every nation
and tribe and people group that are expressions of God's glory in and through them.
This is good. It's good that we have smaller tribes within bigger tribes. It's not a bad thing, but this
truth can move from national or group pride to idolatry. Our nation or our group becomes our primary allegiance.
Its enemies become our enemies, and we justify and dehumanize them. And this is the part that I think we really need to hear.
Its flourishing becomes my highest good, and its power becomes my hope.
And I really think that if we listen to some people talk both inside and outside the church, these people, me, you,
we are putting our ultimate hope in the power of our nation or our political party,
and we're willing to do unchrist-like things in order to help that succeed moving forward.
We announce that Jesus is building a kingdom that is not of this world.
From every tribe, nation, and tongue, nations will rise and fall, but the gates of hell will not prevail against God's kingdom.
Our ultimate hope is in a kingdom that is not of this world.
We do not have to get destroyed by anxiety and lose ourselves because of our nation or our political party,
because we are part of the church and Jesus is building it.
I think this is the last one. I can't remember how many I put in here.
Achievement or success. If I accomplish enough, my life matters.
Depending on where you're at in life, you might come across this in kind of the corporate world or whatever,
but people like find their hope and their identity in who they are and what they do
and how easily or quickly they climb the ladder. If I accomplish enough, my life matters.
Again, affirm. You were created for meaningful work.
This is an original command in the garden to work and to keep, to bless the world around you.
The work that you are doing is likely good work.
But the lie is that you're actually working. Instead of, the gospel says you should work from worth.
This lie, when we usurp it, when we steal it from God, it says that we have to work for worth.
And it's this constant treadmill race of I've got to do more. I've got to go further.
I've got to achieve more so that I can find worth and value.
And the gospel says that your accomplishments are an outworking of your creative creator.
You don't have to achieve worth, but you can receive it. And on and on we could go.
My point is not to give you a script to memorize, because you already know they're not going to come right out and tell you, "My God is my stuff."
And if they do, then your job just got really easy. Right?
It's not to give you a script. It's just to show you that witnessing, evangelizing,
evangelizing, it's so much more creative than just, "Can you read this gospel track and talk to me about it afterwards?"
It's curious. It's creative. It asks questions. It looks people in the eye.
And it affirms. And it testifies that I was there too. And sometimes I still am.
More often than I'd like to be. But let me tell you about a story that's so much bigger than the story that you and I both used to live in.
This is what Buzz does for the other Buzz's. It's really hard to... Grammarly was really confused with what I was doing there.
The application of this message is to know the story of the gospel.
And to allow the gospel to re-narrerate you. To live the story authentically and humbly.
To listen to the story of others and look for creative ways to announce the story of God to those who you are.
To those he's placed in your life. You are a royal priest, a holy nation, being built into a temple for God that can demonstrate the gospel with your life and declare the gospel with your mouth.
I think if we really internalize, if we really understood how good the gospel actually is, we would be less embarrassed and more creative about finding ways to share this news.
He loves this story with gentleness and respect. And even if, I keep coming back to Buzz because it's such a good illustration. If Buzz arrives on the scene, he looks like he's got everything together.
All the other toys except for Woody are enamored by him, right? Like this guy's got swag. He's got confidence. He's got it all together. He's the new toy. He's the cool toy.
And here's the thing. I think oftentimes we're embarrassed about sharing the gospel because some of our friends, they look like Buzz, man. They look like they got it all together.
They look like their lives are better than our lives. They're not like, they look good on the outside. But all of us know, because we were there at one point, that no matter how good we look on the outside, apart from Jesus, there's this longing for more, this peace that's missing.
And so I think sometimes we just forget how good the gospel is. And we look at our friends and our neighbors and our coworkers, and they look like they've got their stuff together.
And my favorite illustration of this is this quote from C.S. Lewis, who, by all accounts, had his stuff together, right? Like esteemed professor of mythology at, somebody help me, Cambridge. Is it Cambridge?
Oxford, somebody. Anybody? Kent. Both. Oxford and Cambridge. Awesome. All right. I knew we would have it, right? Like had it all together, looked put together, smart, whimsome, cunning, all of the things.
I would look at him and be like, I want that guy to be my grandpa, right? And when he reflects on his pre-redeemed state, talks about looking externally
good, and this is what he says about himself internally. At that point, when he looked like Buzz, the overconfident cool guy that all the toys were enamored, he says, "I was a zoo of lusts, a bedlam of ambitions, a nursery of fears, a harem of fondled hatreds. My name was Legion."
And I think sometimes we get intimidated because people in our lives, they look so put together.
And I think we all know, at least the Bible would say, that no matter how put together they look, apart from Jesus, there's something inside of their hearts that is missing.
And sometimes it just takes somebody that loves them enough to listen to their story and be vulnerable and transparent and allow them to say, "You know what? I'm actually a mess."
To which you could say, "Thank God because I thought you were awesome and I was the mess." No, we're all messes. We have to let the gospel of Jesus re-narrate our lives.
We have to listen to the stories of those around us, pray for opportunities to creatively announce the good news of Jesus to them where it meets their story.
This is why, again, this is why we have to study the Bible. We have to live in community with other believers because the way we share the gospel is going to be individualized to each person in our life.
We're going to have to understand their stories so that we can affirm parts of it that are true and show them where they're believing a lie that's ultimately going to lead them to destruction apart from Jesus.
So, unfortunately, it's probably easier to just tell you to memorize the Romans Road.
But I think, my hope, my prayer is that this becomes a spiritual discipline of ours, that we cultivate the ability to first and foremost let God's story re-narrate our story.
And then as we understand that, we look around at the people in our lives and we listen to their stories.
And we do this sacrificially and lovingly with gentleness and respect and patience.
Because witnessing is not a box that we check. It's who we are. It's what we do.
So, from now on, whenever you see Buzz Lightyear, I hope that you think about re-narration, understanding your story in light of God's
greater story, and you remind yourself that your purpose is to come alongside others who don't yet know that they're not really a space ranger.
They're actually an image bearer of God, created for relationship with the Father. Let's pray.
Father, we love you. We thank you for the spiritual truths contained in your word, one unified story,
from beginning to end, inviting people to partner in relationship with you, to spread your goodness to all creation.
And God, you do that incredibly, unwavering, never ending, and humanity continues to fumble the ball,
and you continue to pick the ball back up and put it in our arms, pat us on the back, send us back out onto the field. God, give us spiritual eyes
to see people in our lives, to hear people's stories, to empathize and understand where they're coming from,
and to, with gentleness and compassion, invite them to see that the story's much bigger than they previously believed.
God, may we get the privilege of seeing people's eyes open to your story
for the first time. And if we don't, may we breathe deeply the grace of God, knowing that we did the thing that you invited us to do,
and that we're not God, and it's not our job to intellectually convince somebody to believe something.
God, may this series make us the people who demonstrate and declare your rule and reign more clearly and more visibly,
for your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbors. In Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
I wanted to end, if you would, stand with me. We spent a lot of our time this morning talking about the story of God,
one unified story. As I was thinking about how to conclude this series, I thought about the Apostles' Creed,
and how this is like the summation of church history,
saying this is what we believe about God and the story that we've been invited into.
It's condensed. It's where most Christians find their unity for thousands of years.
And I think it'd just be a really beautiful reminder this morning that this is the story that we've been re-narrated to,
and it is the story that we're invited to re-narrate others to as well.
So if you'd recite the Apostles' Creed with me as we head out, that'd be great.
We believe in God, the Father Almighty, Creator of heaven and earth.
We believe in Jesus Christ, His only Son, our Lord, who was conceived by the Holy Spirit,
born of the Virgin Mary, suffered under Pontius Pilate, was crucified, died, and was buried.
He descended to the dead. On the third day, He rose again.
He ascended into heaven. He is seated at the right hand of the Father.
And He will come again as the living and the dead.
I believe in the Holy Spirit, the Holy Universal Church, the communion of the saints, the forgiveness of sins, the resurrection of the body, and the life everlasting. Amen.
Go in peace, church.
One day, I'll dance on golden sleeves, ride on angels' wings.